Finding Aid for Jack Kausch collection, 1927-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jack Kausch collection 1927-2002, 1976-1994
Kausch, Jack.
1 film reels
1 oversize folders
5 linear feet
07155 Aa 2; UAm
Jack Kausch was a photographer who specialized in family portraits and historical photography. The collection includes still and moving images created and collected by Kausch throughout his career.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 2007 and 2013 by Betsy Kausch (donor no. 9198 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jack Kausch was a photographer who lived and worked in Michigan. He was raised in Detroit and graduated from Cranbrook. He also earned a bachelor's degree in physics and a master's degree in business administration from the University of Michigan. During the Korean War, Kausch joined the Air National Guard and in the late 1950s he worked for his father's construction business. In the 1960s Kausch started work in the GM photographic department developing promotional materials for the company. Finally, in 1976 he opened Jack Kausch Photography where he specialized in family portraits and completed a wide variety of additional projects.
This collection highlights a portion of the projects that Jack Kausch completed during his photographic career. A range of subjects is covered and both original and historical photography is included. The collection is divided into two series: Photographs and Other Visual Materials.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automobile industry.; Churches--Michigan.; Cicadas.; Detroit-Windsor Tunnel (Detroit, Mich. and Windsor, Ont.); Ferries--Michigan--Detroit.; Ferries--Ontario--Windsor.; Fox Theatre Building (Detroit, Mich.); General Motors Corporation.; General Motors Corporation. Fisher Body Division. Fleetwood Plant.; Kausch, Jack.; Poletown (Detroit, Mich.); Stroh Brewery Company.; Tunnels.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes four subseries: Automotive History; Detroit, Michigan; Gordon W. Lloyd; and Michigan, General. Most of the photographs are in the form of negatives or slides; however some photographic prints are included throughout the collection.
  - Automotive History
    The Automotive History subseries features materials about the history of the automobile, particularly General Motors and the Fleetwood Plant in Detroit. The history of the Fleetwood Plant, where many famous and luxurious automobile bodies were built, is covered in photographic negatives. Additionally, there are several photographic prints of presidents and other well-known individuals posing with GM automobiles.
    - Airplane assembly facility circa 1910s (Box 1)
      (see also oversize folder)
    - Automobile assembly (Box 1)
    - "The Changing Nature of the Auto Body", (photographic slides (Box 1)
    - Parade of Progress 1946 (Box 1)
    - Presidents and other celebrities (Box 1)
    - Promotional events (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      (include Fleetwood plant, tanks, etc.; see also oversize folder)
    - "People, Pride and Progress", 3 folders; (negative strips (Box 1)
      (produced for Fisher Body -- Fleetwood)
  - Detroit, Michigan
    The Detroit, Michigan subseries features photographic prints, slides, and negatives of various local landmarks. These include historic and contemporary images of the following: the Detroit-Windsor Tunnel under construction and in operation; the restored Fox Theater; Poletown throughout its history; and the Stroh's factory during production.
    - Aerial Photography (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of photographers on aerial shoot)
    - Detroit-Windsor Tunnel
      - Cut-and-cover Section (Box 1)
      - Dedication Day (Box 1)
      - Ferries (Box 1)
      - General (Box 1)
      - Shield-driven Section (Box 1)
      - Terminal Buildings and Ventilation Tower (Box 1)
    - Fox Theater (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Poletown (Box 1)
    - Stroh's
      - General (Box 1)
      - Production August 1977 (Box 1)
  - Gordon W. Lloyd project circa 1990s
    The Gordon W. Lloyd subseries is an extensive set of material documenting many buildings designed by this 19th century architect. Lloyd emigrated from England and worked in Michigan and nearby states. He designed several churches and cathedrals, as well as secular buildings including the Northern Michigan Asylum and a few private residences. Various formats including photographic prints, slides, and negatives, as well as a small amount of textual research material comprise this series.
    - Buildings
      (arranged by approximate date of construction)
      - Christ Church (Detroit, Mich.) 1861 (Box 1)
      - Trinity Church (Marshall, Mich.) 1861 (Box 2)
      - Central Methodist Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.) 1866-1867 (Box 2)
      - Church of the Good Shepherd (Allegan, Mich.) circa 1866-1869 (Box 2)
      - Trinity Church (Columbus, Ohio) 1866-1869 (Box 2)
      - Saint Andrew's Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) 1867 (Box 2)
      - Saint James' Church (Grosse Ile, Mich.) 1867 (Box 2)
      - Saint James' Church (Milwaukee, Wis.) 1867-1870 (Box 2)
      - Church of the Holy Spirit (Gambier, Ohio) 1869-1870 (Box 2)
      - Trinity Cathedral (Pittsburgh, Pa.) 1870-1871 (Box 2)
      - Christ Church (Springfield, Ohio) 1872 (Box 2)
      - All Saints Church (Saugatuck, Mich.) 1872-1873 (Box 2)
      - Church of the Ascension (Buffalo, New York) 1872-1873 (Box 2)
      - Saint Paul's Church (Flint, Mich.) 1873 (Box 2)
      - Saint Paul's Church (Marquette, Mich.) 1873 (Box 2)
      - Church of the Good Shepherd (Ogden, Utah) 1874-1875 (Box 2)
    - Buildings Undated
      - Saint John's Church (Saginaw, Mich.) 1883 (Box 2)
      - Saint Luke's Church (Kalamazoo, Mich.) 1883-1884 (Box 2)
      - Saint Paul's Church (Medina, Ohio) 1884 (Box 2)
      - Traverse City Asylum 1885 (Box 2)
      - Cathedral of St. Paul (Erie, Pa.) (Box 2)
      - Gatehouses (Box 2)
      - Little Cote (Box 2)
      - Morpeth, Ontario (Box 2)
      - Other or Unknown (Box 2)
      - University of Detroit, Mercy (Box 2)
      - Various Churches (Box 2)
    - Drawings and Furniture (Box 2)
    - Family Gravestones (Box 2)
    - Research (Box 2)
    - Various Visual Materials
      - Digital files, 1 floppy disks 3.5"; 13 optical disks CDs (Box 3)
        (master copies of images; Photoshop, TIFF, and JPEG files)
      - Indexed Photographs (backup copies of images) (Box 3)
      - Negatives (Box 3)
  - Michigan, General
    The Michigan, General subseries contains an extensive set of photographic slides documenting flora and fauna throughout the state; wildflowers are especially highlighted. The series also contains a small amount of material on the University of Michigan and the city of Birmingham.
    - Birmingham (Box 3)
    - Flora and Fauna (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Football Stadium (Box 3)
- Other Visual Materials
  The Other Visual Materials series is comprised of three subseries: Videotapes and Motion Pictures, and Detroit-Windsor Tunnel. Included in the subseries are several videos and a few films that were a part or product of Kausch's moving image projects. The videos and films include a thirty-minute natural history documentary about cicadas in Michigan and a fifteen-minute promotional piece on the history and future of Cadillac. In general, they cover a range of subjects including local history, automotive history, and natural history. Also included are various formats and versions of Kausch's 1980 film made for the fiftieth anniversary of the Detroit-Windsor Tunnel
  - Videotapes
    (VHS unless otherwise noted)
    - 17-Year Cicadas (Magicicada septendecim) (Box 4)
      (tape no. 1)
    - The Boat Builders of Les Cheneaux (Box 4)
      (tape no. 2)
    - Children of the Holocaust, Parts 1 and 2 (Box 4)
      (tape no. 3)
    - Detroit Country Day, Middle School, Presentation (Box 4)
      (tape no. 4)
    - Flying Tigers, 529th Fighter Squadron, 311th Fighter Group (Box 4)
      (tape no. 5)
    - From Ice to Islands (Box 4)
      (tape no. 6)
    - Passage to the Future (Box 4)
      (tape no. 7)
    - A Sense of History: Andrew Wineland Tanner, Photographs of the Late 19th and Early 20th Century (Box 4)
      (tape no. 8)
    - Solidarity, Part I, (U-matic (Box 4)
      (tape no. 9)
    - Solidarity, Part II, (U-matic (Box 4)
      (tape no. 10)
    - Teamwork and Technology Cadillac Style (Box 4)
      (tape no. 11)
    - Andrew Tanner Historical Photographs Slide Show 1995 (Box 4)
      (tape no. 12)
  - Motion Pictures
    - The Fleetwood Story: People Pride and Progress, Local 15 insert (Box 4)
    - UAW Local 15 and Fleetwood Strike Film 1950s (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 4)
      (film reels stored in accordion folder)
    - 17-Year Cicadas (Magicicada septendecim) (Reel 1)
  - Detroit-Windsor Tunnel (Box 5)
    - 1980 Print, 2 16 mm film reels (Box 5)
    - 1980 Mag, 16 mm film reel (Box 5)
    - A Track and Internegative, 2 16 mm film reels (Box 5)
    - Video Master (U-matic videocassette) (Box 5)
    - Revised A & B Rolls 1990, 2 16 mm film reels (Box 5)
    - From Revised A & B Rolls 1990, 1 inches video reel (Box 5)
    - 1990 Revision Work Print, B Track, Title Trims, 3 16 mm film reels (Box 5)